Ditch those rookie trading apps. Get Tasty Trade,
the platform for serious traders. Chart with 300
plus indicators. Know your profit odds and move
fast. Trade stocks, options, futures, and more all
in one account. See why serious traders choose
Tasty Trade. Visit tastyrade.com. Tasty Trade
Inc. is a registered broker dealer and FINRA NFA
and SIPC member. There's not a single formula for
this. Either someone who's taken a small amount of
money and turned it into a huge amount of money.
And to take two extreme examples in the current
book, two of the traders have literally gone from
sub $50,000 accounts to close to a half billion.
That's sort of a dramatic but real example of what
I mean by a spectacular increase in wealth. Right.
Then the other one is traders who just haven't
made like a ton of money really, but they've
have an unbelievable return to risk. So two other
traders in this book, one of them has not had a
losing month, but it's like steady. He doesn't
make a fortune. He basically earns a living as a
trader. So he's like, So when Jack and I met, we
had this firm belief that there were some amazing
traders out there globally. And along the path, we
realized that it was one thing to find a talented
trader, but if they were in a country where maybe
they didn't have a regulatory jurisdiction or
they didn't have the legal structure set up,
they couldn't really properly, you know, have the
institutional infrastructure to manage outside
capital. And so it became almost another barrier
to entry for them to transition from a really good
trader who's really focused to then aspiring
to become the Steven Cohen of the world that
they actually launch a fund in managing capital.
The idea of the accelerator and it was you know
how do we find that talented trader let's say the
market wizard quality trader and then come around
them and provide them with the infrastructure uh
the mentorship it could be regulatory it could
be marketing the the distribution the access
to capital so that they can be focused at what
they're doing and then we can provide them with
with all the the needed resources for them to
potentially manage money and then compete against
some of the largest hedge funds in the world.
Perhaps somebody who's listening to the show who
who's aspiring, you know, they they want to manage
money, but also they've been they're riskaverse
and intelligent enough to know that they're not
going to spend a lot of capital setting up a
structure of a fund to potentially raise money
from outside investors that they have no network
from, right? And so this is almost like legging
into this opportunity. Markets, speculation,
and risk. This is the Chat with Traders podcast.
Oh yes, we're on episode 308 of the Chat Traders
podcast and this is a special one. I'm Tessa Dao,
co-host with Ian Cox, and we're joined by
Jack Schwager, best known as the author of the
legendary Market Wizard series and also co-founder
of FundSeeder, together with his partner and
fellow co-founder, Emanuel Balerie. We dig into
what it actually takes to be considered for a
market wizard's book. There isn't one formula, but
Jack definitely looks for standout performance.
traders who've achieved the kind of results most
would think impossible, but it's not impossible.
Over the years, we've had traders who were
featured in Market Wizards that eventually
appeared on our podcast. But as Jack described the
qualities he looks for now, I couldn't help but
think I wouldn't be surprised if some of our other
guests that we've had on the show who've never
been in the books before might show up in a future
volume. That's an exciting thought and we shall
wait and see. One of the parts of our conversation
that stood out to me as a developing trader was
the razor's edge between surviving and blowing
up and why it so often comes down to position
sizing and planning your exit in advance. From
there, the conversation branches into the kind
of obsession with process and routines that Jack
has consistently seen in the traders featured in
his market wizards books. An obsession that allows
them to keep adapting as markets change. We also
talk about whether timeless strategies like trend
following can still hold up in today's markets
and a surprising paradox Jack points out about
fundamentals and risk that might change the way
you think. Then we shift to FundSeeder a platform
co-founded by Emanuel and Jack built to discover
and evaluate undiscovered trading talent from
around the world. Emanuel explains how it works,
how they verify performance, evaluate capacity
and process, and how through the fund cedar rise
accelerator, now part of RQSI, a hedge fund and
seeding firm with a long track record of backing
emerging managers. They help top performers get
the infrastructure and seed capital to scale.
And here's the part that should excite many of you
listening. They're actively searching for the next
generation of talented traders, people with the
potential to move from trading their own accounts
to managing outside capital as professional fund
managers. Very few will ultimately make the cut,
but every great manager starts somewhere. And
if you've been honing your craft and building
a real track record, why not you? So, if
you're serious about your craft, you'll
love this episode. More information and links
are in the show notes. So without further ado,
ladies and gentlemen, we are so pleased to
present Jack Schwager and Emmanuel Balerie.
Well, everyone, I'd like to welcome both famous
Jack Schwager, author of the Market Wizards books,
and Emanuel Balerie, who is the founder of Fund
Cedar with Jack. And I'd like to start off with
Jack. Uh Jack, welcome back to Jack with Traders.
Um I think it's been seven or eight years since
you were last on here. Yeah, it's been a number
of years. I'm not sure how many. Yeah. Uh and uh
you're up you've written a lot of uh great
books. Um part of the Market Wizard series
of books. Are you up to How many has it been?
Six already. Uh I'm working on number six. Oh,
you're working on number six. Okay, great. I read
your first Market Wizards book back in 1994 and
uh that inspired me to get into trading. Um
do you have a release date on for your book?
Uh the release date is um I think it's going to
be around June. Yeah, looking forward to it. So
maybe July don't remember the exact date, but it's
early summer. Okay. Do do you have all the slots
taken up? You found all the traders done all the
interviews. uh the actual confirmed list of who's
going to be in the book. Uh haven't officially
confirmed that yet, you know, so just waiting
until the book is actually finalized in manuscript
before I kind of described, you know, go into more
detail on it. And could you share with us kind
of what are the criteria to get entrance into
your books? Yeah. Okay. So obviously the first
criteria is performance you know and then the
question is what kind of performance and there's
not a single formula for this. So basically I
look for one or two things uh either someone who's
taken a small amount of money and turned it into
a huge amount of money. Um there's a and to take
two extreme examples in the current book two of
the traders have literally gone from sub $50,000
accounts to close to a half billion. Half billion.
Yeah. Right. Right. Or 500 million if you want to
round it to millions. Um, so that's a you can get
that's sort of a dramatic uh but real example
of of what I mean by a spectacular increase in
wealth. Right? Then the other one is traders
who just uh haven't made like a ton of money
really. I mean make x millions whatever it is but
they've have an unbelievable return to risk. So,
two other traders in this book, one of them has
not had a losing month and in well 11 years now
that can can be shown because he went off on
his own, but then he was a prop trader and I
don't doubt him when he says he didn't lose money
in those, you know, prior few years as well. So,
he's probably gone 15 years without a losing
month, uh, you know, without a single losing
month. So, but it's like steady. He doesn't
make a fortune. He basically earns a living
as a trader. So he's like making uh about I don't
know 300 400,000 a year sort of makes money every
month. Um and but that type of consistency another
trader um who's had a long track record is able to
track back further. I forget how many years now uh
it was over 15. But uh in his case he's had five
losing months all pretty small. In in the first
case, you can't even calculate some return risk
ratios because you've got you get infin infinity
because you have no no divisor that's negative,
right? But you get and the second trade with a few
losing months, you get this these extraordinary
return risk numbers that are just mind-boggling.
So it's either of those two uh as far as the
performance side and then there are other criteria
in terms of that it can't be it can be for a short
period because you know anybody can have a good
five years right or whatever I typically try to
get a minimum of 10 cases is 15 or 20 or even if
the official track record as is the case in this
book as well sometimes can't go all the way back
because they were prop traders before, but they've
traded for a long time. So, I'm I'm getting
people who've demonstrated it for lengths of
time. Uh very rarely will I make an exception to
the 10 year to the 10 year rule. Occasionally for
some compelling story, but uh but it's always at
least close to 10 and 95 plus percent of the time
it's you know it's well well more than that. Wow.
Yeah, those are outrageous returns. Uh in some of
your previous interviews, you've mentioned that
you were looking for the truths of the markets
that will still be true a 100red years from now.
And you brought up the challenges of human nature
as one of the key sticking points and how human
nature works against us. And you you referenced
a a funny image of uh monkeys throwing darts at
a Wall Street page often do better than humans.
And my question is could these results be
dramatically improved by just position sizing
appropriately for each person's psychology? Uh
well yes I mean position sizing is an important
element and it is a downfall of many traders. Um
it well there there's a matter of cutting losses
you in terms of risk management right matter
of cutting losses and then there's a matter of
position sizing. So if you size too large uh you
can cut your losses but if you were to be risking
10% of your capital on on any given trade and and
here let me be clear I don't mean that you buy a
stock that takes up 10% of your capital. That
is not, you know, that's only risk attempts on
your capital if you're holding it to zero, right?
But I'm talking about you have a plan, you have
either a stop in or a plan or some defined risk
point. So you may you may alloc 10% of your AUM,
but you're only risking one or two%. So that's
fine. So the mistake if people put on a position
too large um and uh then it can become uh a very
damaging you know one bad trade can become very
very damaging. In fact a number of the traders in
this new book as great as they are as spectacular
as they are had some hair raising episodes
where position sizing was part of the problem.
people before they get into trading and they have
their jobs, they can treat their jobs seriously
and know that they have to study and work hard and
and follow rules. So why do you think um many new
traders can't treat trading like a job? I mean
they've got their skin in they got a lot of skin
in the game, their own money and hopefully avoid
most of the pitfalls of human nature that has
plagued us from the beginning days. The reason is
because uh I think maybe the probably the majority
and I don't know how large of the majority of
people get into trading don't appreciate that
to really succeed and you can see this again
in this new book. I keep on thinking there's
so when I'm answering these questions there's so
many glaring examples to prove this where these
these people didn't just trading wasn't just a
hobby. It wasn't just a even wasn't even a job.
It was it was, you know, an overwhelming
obsession and just kind of capitalizing
all their time and energy. And the the fellow I
mentioned who never had a losing month, I mean,
he literally gets up at 3:30 to check to check the
markets, goes back to sleep at and then comes back
at 5:30 and then doesn't wind up until 8:00 p.m.
So, wow. I mean that's the kind of devotion that
that you get and uh types of intense analysis
and study that some of these traders do. Um,
one fellow just uh they're talking about going
through thousands of of cases of SEC filings and
just becoming almost a walking encyclopedia of
and and categorizing it of SEC filing comes out,
you know, dec figuring out what's important,
what happened in each case, what's not important.
it it just the amount of work that they devote
to this is is sometimes staggering. Um and one
of the other traders uh basically not only would
be trading who was a prop trader trading he no
longer now that he's made a fair amount of money
he's kind of eased off a bit but but in his early
part of his career when he was a prop trader uh he
would um not only spend the entire day trading and
do the analysis afterwards but he would literally
record key parts of his trading and then replay
them and retrade those things out of So that's the
kind of devotion. Now you think about people who
get into trading because they want to they want
to be a trader, they want to make money. Um they
don't have that type of devotion with exceptions,
but for the most part they don't. And I think that
people don't appreciate who really excel. I mean
you have to have a talent for two. That's that's
that's another element. But even if you have
the talent, you really have to do the hard work.
And the hard work as in just investing time uh
or learning everything there is to learn about
it because you mentioned the guy that looked at
SEC filings and well the hard work I first of all
you have to define what your strategy is and and
and that that it's what you want to do and what
you feel you have an edge at. But then it's just
doing everything you can to hone that strategy.
And it goes it goes beyond that. It's not like
learning a craft. You know, you're a carpenter
and you learn every technique and you get really
better and better and you've like get to a certain
point and is that that's it. And now you know how
to do everything any type of cabinetry and and
do perfectly and and you've devoted your life to
being a perfect carpenter. In trading, it's worse
uh than that. I mean, because you get to a point
where you're skilled and everything's going fine,
but markets keep on changing and in almost every
case, I I can't think of a single interview in
this book where the trader didn't go through
adaption phases of change and sometimes where
they end up could be quite different from
where they started. So it's not only a
matter of devoting all this time and energy
to whatever the technique is at the moment,
but it's also a matter of being open to the
need and the signals that that particular
methodology is losing its efficacy and you now
need to adapt into some other strategy. Um,
one of the one the trader I mentioned who had
only five losing months and very high return
risk who by the way is himself he runs a u he
runs a prop training firm he co-founded and
uh he's he estimates he's he's trained over
200 people in his day he trainers in his day
um uh but he he emphasizes that the importance of
always maintaining the mentality of a trainee. In
other words, he even though he's got 25 years of
trading experience, even though he's tra train 200
traders, he still keeps himself at the mentality
where he's like a trainee who's just get trying
to get in, trying to break in and trying to find
stuff that works. And so he tries to keep himself
in that framework because he knows that whatever
is working today in many cases won't be working
a year from now or five years or whatever. So he
tries to always be looking for new new techniques
or how his current methods have to change. I see.
So it's almost like he's trying to anticipate the
next change in market behavior. like if he was
learning how to trade uh when the market was in
a strong trending bull market and then the market
goes choppy sideways for a while. Is that kind of
it? He's trying to anticipate different market
conditions and learn ahead of time. It's more a
matter of trying to in his case trying to find
different patterns or quirks or inefficiencies
in the market. And you know he gives examples
in the interview where for example at one time
the idea of figuring out which stocks were going
into the index the let's call it the S&P or any
other index and which were coming out trying
to anticipate that be long the ones that are
going in and short the ones that are going to come
out. That was a great strategy for an edge because
once it goes in all these institutions have to
rebalance their portfolio. So you know, you know,
new stock comes into the S&P, it's going to get
a lot of B. I mean, it's it's an obvious thing.
So the for a few few years that worked, but then
it became too too well known and away and it's no
longer works. Um so and these things disappear
for sometimes explainable reasons and sometimes
for reasons which are a mystery. Uh he mentions
he had this that he used to trade the VIX. He had
a particular pattern he traded in the VIX and
it depended on the time of day and it was like
a really reliable pattern. It was an important
strategy of his and then for some reason and he
couldn't explain it but when Russia invaded
Ukraine right after that the patent stopped
working and never worked again you know so some of
these things god knows what the relationship would
be between the invasion and the VIX but yeah
maybe it's just coincidental but the point is
things that work uh very often will stop working
and sometimes they may come back but sometimes
Chat with Traders is brought to you by Tasty
Trade. Tired of trading on rookie apps? Then
get the platform for serious trading. Tasty Trade.
Tasty Trade gives you the tools to trade your way.
Chart your heart out with over 300 indicators.
Know your odds with probability of profit and
move fast with Quick Roll. Trade what you want
and trade it your way. Stocks, options, futures,
and more. All in one account on one platform. No
wonder why serious traders choose Tasty Trade.
Visit tastyrade.com and see for yourself.
Tasty Trade Inc. is a registered broker
dealer and member of FINRA, NFA, and SIPC. M uh
how much of that do you think is attributed to
um other traders hearing about it and then they
that tra that particular strategy gets crowded
and do have you found any particular strategies or
ideas that maybe worked for a while and then were
discovered or didn't work for a while but then
forgotten and then later came back into vogue
almost like an old style of of fashion clothing
or something like that. Yeah. Well, uh maybe
the best example is trend following, right? So,
when I did the first market wizard into uh book
um and is and so I'm interviewing people, this
is in uh I'm interviewing them in 88, but we're
talking about careers which go back in their cases
to the 60s or at least the 70s, right? And so back
in the 60s and 70s, there's no computer. Forget
about supercomputers, forget about corn shops.
Uh I mean you didn't even have a PC really uh
until into the 80s was just the beginning of it.
So um so the people like Ed Sakakota who was in
that first book who was just doing simple trend
following stuff. He was I think his background was
an engineer and he got a job on Wall Street so he
could use the the main frames back the main
frames and I knew exactly what he was talking
about because when Iris my senior year in college
I remember doing uh uh programming on the same on
the same main frame as an IBM 360 took up a good
part of a small room and it was punch cards and
you know it it had the power I don't know what
fraction of a iPhone power it had whatever anyway
um but in those days that That's all. So he just
needed access to computer and he he did some basic
trend following things and he did phenomenally
well on that and and and also like somebody
like Dennis is a classic example who used trend
following to build a fortune and uh you know that
all worked great in the 60s7 particularly the 70s
even into the 80s but at beginning in the then as
computers became more popular and platforms and
software became available. It sort of everybody
and their brother could could do trend following,
right? So it it became too accessible, too easy,
too popular and the the concept of trend following
does have real rationale behind it and and that is
because for many many markets once a trend begins
there are very good reasons for it to continue.
So, uh, you know, if the Fed changes its policy,
rarely does the Fed change from tightening to
loosening and then then three months later go back
to tightening. So, typically once they once they
begin on a course of tightening and loosening,
it often will just continue for for a long time.
current in terms of currency uh valuation central
banks trying to control their currency values
they decide or make an agreement to go in a given
direction like the plaza cord doesn't you know but
once that happens it tends to go for years it just
so there are real reasons why and and you take
commodities you get surpluses and then it takes a
long time for that surplus to to kind of work its
way to work its way down and then eventually you
get to the point where it discourages expansion
and production or whatever. Uh so I mean true
for something like a copper takes takes a year
you know if copper goes into surplus and you
discourage new mining and you discourage and
some old mines close and whatever it takes a while
a very long time to open new mines if there's a
shortage eventually. So there's reasons why trends
exist but what the market has done I mean I don't
know who said it but uh you know the market sort
of fools the greatest paraphrasing here uh you
know we'll act in a way it will fool the greatest
number of people the most time so even though it
can't get even though the trend will still occur
it will occur in such a way that it will cut to
pieces some trend followers by just these whips or
actions which look like complete changes of trend
and uh not just minor pullbacks that oh I got
faked out by this one pull no but these really
big declines that uh that and then the market may
go right back you see it more in stocks by the way
you see in stocks you get this extreme volatility
like that because of earnings and things of that
nature uh but you get it in all markets so it
becomes more difficult to profit from from trend
following because of that whipssaw action becoming
more pronounced. I think I haven't ever done the
analysis and I don't know anybody who ever has. It
would be an interesting analysis. But I would bet
that if someone measured uh how drawn the markets
were to let's say reactions in a trend of beyond
a certain percentage size different thresholds I
will bet that that has increased and become more
frequent over time uh relative to what it was
say in the 60s7s and 80s. you highlighted some
of the uh examples of say fundamental factors that
are behind a a strong trend because there's some
good reasons why a trend is in place. Uh in one
of your previous interviews you mentioned that
uh fundamentals worked in contradiction to risk
management. Why would that that's well here's the
crazy thing. So uh you know if you in technical
what one advantage of technical analysis is that
for most approaches in technical analysis if
you're wrong it yeah it it will indicate that
your technical reason for being in the market
is wrong and it will tell you to get out if you
follow your own approach. Uh the trouble with
fundamentals is let's say I do an analysis of
uh of the of the of corn or whatever. U let's go
market X and let's say I I say market X should be
at $7 and it's currently at um $5. Okay. So okay
that's I got my reason this market I've done the
analysis that based on supply and demand I think
it should it needs to go up because there's not
not enough supply to clear demand you know that at
this price so we need to bring demand down price
has to go up okay so that's that's fine but then
then the market goes down to 450 let's say for
whatever reason and let's say it doesn't change
the fundamentals so I'm sitting there Well, if it
was a good buy at five, it's now a better buy at
450. And that's the key here is that's consistent
with the methodology. Okay? It's not like I'm
ignoring my methodology. I've got my analysis and
my analysis tells me seven. Nothing has changed.
The market's going from five to 450. So, the only
logical thing is not only to hold, but perhaps
even to add. So that's the the the intrinsic
nature of fundamentals is such that uh the more
it goes against you if nothing has changed in your
analysis the the the more you should add to the
position. So that's what I meant and that that's
what makes fundamental analysis difficult. Um and
the other thing is that fundamental analysis is
very poorly attuned generally speaking to timing.
So there's not a consistency between fundamental.
Well, sometimes you get you get a change and
uh Okay, so you you you get a change that
uh uh that um some new information comes out and
things change and and the price changes all I mean
earnings reports in stocks are a good example.
So surprise earnings report that okay and and
the price adjusts. So sometimes it's obvious,
you know, which direction, but a lot of times
broad fundamentals, there's no real timing to the
shifting fundamentals and the actual price action.
Sometimes the fundamentals proceed, sometimes they
lag. Uh it can be all over the place. The only
time ironically that fundamentals are good for
timing and this is just my opinion is in a kind of
contrarian way. So if if the market uh gets some
bullish news and it goes up as starts to go up
as expected and then and then declines and let's
say closes lower on the day that can be indicative
of a change in you know the market has changed
direction. So in that case where the fundamentals
don't do what you expect them to do uh that might
be useful timing but that's ironically opposite
to what the fundamentals said. You've said uh
multiple times in the past that one of the uh most
important points is to know when you'll get out
before you get in. Since most traders are used to
uh setting their their exits at, you know, one
R, two R, two times what they risk or three times
what they risk, doesn't one run the risk of uh
getting out too early and not capturing, you know,
the trend is your friend and let your winners
run and those other apherisms that has helped
some traders uh make great profits off of a few
trades that overcame many of their smaller losses.
Yeah, I mean of of course that this is just a
general point. Obviously, if you're using any
type of uh exit point for risk protection, you
always and it's not theoretical. Traders who
use do that will of will get experience of being
stopped out right before the market turns multiple
times and you know in their trading career. It's
unavoidable. But the key is it also avoids any any
loss larger than what you prepared that what
you've decided to allow in the beginning. And
that's a trade-off. And it's a trade-off which uh
is necessary in my opinion. And and by the way,
that that line know where you get where you'll get
out before you get in. That's uh give credit where
credit is due. That that is a quote from Bruce
Governor in the first market wizards book. Um, and
it's the reason I like that quote so much and why
I've used it so often is not only does it provide
very effective risk management, the key there is
that because it's the word before, because you're
making decision before you get in, you're making
it at a point of objectivity. So it's different
than if you stay with the position without any
stop and the market starts going against you and
now you have to make decisions but your decisions
can always be clouded by the fact that you're
you're in you're in the position that that kills
your subjectivity. So your object objectivity I'm
sorry. Uh so the idea of making that decision
before you enter their position means you're
making it from a rational cool point based on what
your approach is and you say okay I'm buying the
market at at 50. If I'm right it shouldn't go
to 45 and that's where you put your stop. So,
uh, you you have a rational reason before you got
into the trade when you were fully objective for
picking that stop and if it gets hit, well, that
was your pre analysis that if it got it shouldn't
go there and if it did get there, you were wrong.
Even if it eventually rebounds and goes higher.
So let's transition a little bit about and uh
to the topic of fund seedar and uh share with
us how you got involved with that and kind of
what was the inspiration and also I'd like to
hear from Emanuel as well. Sure. So I'll give
my comment because Emanuel is the one who should
talk mostly on this topic. But uh the idea was
presented to me uh by Emanuel at the time. Uh
I was doing some consulting for a firm uh that
he was with a brokerage firm and uh we were at
a conference together and having dinner I believe
and he said, "Jack, I want to pitch this idea to
you." And he pitched the idea of FundSeeder. And
I said, "Yeah, it's a, you know, I'm I'm I'm one
who's always prepared to shoot down ideas." Um,
Emanuel will tell you that, but I said, "Yeah,
that's that's that's a good idea." And, uh, so
that's why I So, my only involvement was was via
Emanuel who had the original idea. Oh, great.
So, Emanuel, I'd like to hear from you kind of
um a little bit about your background and then
uh what made you uh get involved with Fun Cedar
or create it for that matter. Yeah. Well, Jack's
humble. He's he was a true co-founder. There would
be no FundSeeder with without him. Um we we were
actually co-portfolio managers for a fund and we
were aligned in terms of believing that we could
give capital to emerging managers. Um and we had
traveled the world. Um you were Portugal all over
um finding some of these emerging managers. And
so really the the the reason for fund cedar was
where we wanted to have edge to be able to uh
discover uh undiscovered traders uh undiscovered
managers and then somehow help them along the way
in terms of becoming institutional or giving them
capital. So our our thesis was in a world you know
where like Jack was talking about when he was you
know coding you know in a mainframe computer it
had rapidly evolved where people had access now
to information technology but on the other side
the same big hedge fund managers were controlling
a bulk of the assets and so FundSeeder was looking
to dem democratize how we can give access
to talented traders from all over the globe.
wherever they might be and and then uh
provide them with analytics and Jack
was involved in this in terms of um you know
metrics that we could you know quantitatively
uh evaluate and then if we found the good ones
we'd give them capital and so that was that was
the the the idea behind FundSeeder. So uh how does
it work? How would it how would you find these
traders or how would traders show you that uh hey
they're hey I'm a good trader? Well, first of all,
we're giving them a shot in an opportunity,
right? So, we I think the last time I looked,
we had over we had signups for two funds here from
over 120 countries. So, no matter where you're at,
you don't have to be in New York City, you don't
have to be part in London, you can sign up to
FundSeeder. And the idea would be you would be
connecting your brokerage account. Um so we have
connection with interactive brokers and adding
others or you can even upload your files which
we classify as unverified and and then we can see
how you can and you as well as a trader can see
how you stack up against your peers or you could
stack up against others and if you're really good
enough or or you're not good enough. And um and so
that's that that was the process, right? providing
almost if you think about the baseball analogy
of a baseball farm system, opening it up to
everybody and let the top 1% have an opportunity
to to potentially manage capital. Have you been
able to accumulate any stats on okay what type
of assets they trade? Are they systematic versus
discretionary or any information regarding number
of trades, draw downs, that kind of thing? Yeah.
So the analytics and you know that funded provides
um look they look exactly what you mentioned in
terms of draw downs you know gain of pain ratio
which you know Jack is fond of you know volatility
correlation to other markets and so that gives us
that initial uh sort of viewpoint of you know does
potentially does the trader have scale or edge and
then um so that becomes something that is valuable
to to the traders who sign up to the platform.
Um, do you have any data on like what percentage
of traders can uh match or beat the S&P 500 or how
many end up um losing money um or blowing up their
accounts? Well, I I think Jack when when Jack and
I started this and it was initially just an idea,
we always thought that the top 1% would even be
good enough to potentially manage money. And so
from a sourcing perspective that that's pretty
accurate, right? uh you know earlier in this in
this podcast Jack was talking about how I mean the
the top market wizards you know are hardworking
you know extremely disciplined are like almost
you know f they're so focused on what they're
doing and that shows in terms of the data that
we're seeing of of the talented traders that have
you know you know top 1% in terms of risk adjusted
numbers we haven't looked at the ones who have say
blown up or um you know you know how many of them
churned through it because our our goal was really
to find those top 1% that that even before they
signed up to fund Cedar um had you know had u had
had excellent metrics and that's really the reason
we even kind of were talking as you know when we
talked about about the show a lot of I would
imagine a lot of the traders that are listening
to your podcast are are highly educated They're
they're they're always looking to learn from other
traders and you mentioned three of them that
ended up being are going to be in Jack's book.
So that's really the profile of of the traders
we are looking to have sign up on phone cereal
traders from a quantitative and qualitative
approach to get included in your Sure. Yeah.
In the finals. Quantitatively, you know, it's
we're looking for managers and traders that
h have high risk adjusted numbers whether,
you know, um so that filters it, you know,
return to risk levels. Um we're looking to
see if they're trading uh their strategy has
capacity. So someone could if the trader could
only you know you know trade on $2 million or
they're trading small small cap stocks or some
type of short selling that's probably not a fit
for them to be able to transition to manage
other people's capital because the capacity
is not there and they probably wouldn't want
to take on the additional capacity as well. So
quantitatively the data speaks for itself. But
then qualitatively when we have conversations
and Jack and I have had many over the years
uh with these traders we try to to understand
where their edge is at right and you know how can
they articulate their strategy. You know what sets
them apart from others that would say that they're
doing exactly the same thing. Um so we look at the
person we look at how they articulate what they're
doing. Um, and then from a business perspective,
and this is the point of transition from
someone who's just trading their own money,
do they have almost that that business
desire to scale and grow their business? Um,
and that becomes a almost a different evolution
in their in in their in their trading history,
if you will. Uh, I understand that you have
an accelerator called FundSeeder. is that
u or emerging wizards. Um yeah so if you think
about the genesis of really almost what we what we
have done with funds. So when Jack and I met, we
had this firm belief that there were some amazing
traders out there globally. And along the path, we
realized that it was one thing to find a talented
trader, but if they were in a country where
maybe they didn't have a regulatory jurisdiction
or they didn't have the legal structure set
up, they couldn't really properly, you know,
have the institutional infrastructure to manage
outside capital. And so it became almost another
barrier to entry for them to transition from
a really good trader who's really focused to
then aspiring to become the Steven Cohen of
the world that they actually launch a fund
in managing capital. And so the idea of the
accelerator and and it was you know how do we
uh find that talented trader let's say the market
wizard quality trader and then come around them
and provide them with the infrastructure uh the
mentorship um it could be regulatory it could be
marketing the the distribution the access to
capital so that they can be focused at what
they're doing and then we can have them provide
them with with all the the needed resources for
them to potentially manage money and then compete
against some of the largest hedge funds in the
world. And so so an example I would give is you
know you if you're familiar with the Silicon
Valley where they had all these accelerators like
Y Combinator you had Airbnb or other companies
where there were strong founders they had some
some type of track record of success but the
network and the the the the resources provided by
some of these venture firms helped them accelerate
where they became the massive companies that they
are. So, we're trying to do the exact same thing
for perhaps somebody who's listening to the show
who who's who's aspiring, you know, they they want
to manage money, but also they've been they're
really um uh they're riskaverse and intelligent
enough to know that they're not going to spend a
lot of capital setting up a structure of a fund to
potentially raise money from outside investors
that they have no network from. Right? And so
this is almost like legging into this opportunity.
So just to confirm, so they're initially they're
trading with their own capital and their own
accounts and their trades are verified. Yeah.
So to so for fund cedar we have two options.
if they connect their brokerage accounts
uh their trades are verified and if they're not
part of a compat we don't have a you know their
broker is not compatible they can upload uh an XLS
file to see to use our analytics to see how they
can compare and then we can verify afterwards
through statements um or or other means to
make sure that their their data is is is real and
accurate. Mhm. Uh, how would you say what are the
differences of what you offer from the many online
terms that seem to be everywhere these days?
Excuse the last interruption here. This is Tessa.
We hope you're enjoying this episode so far. If
you love the podcast, please give Chat with
Traders the best review you can on whatever
platform you're listening from. This will help us
to keep the episodes coming. Also, if you haven't
subscribed to our email list, please hop on to
chatwithtraders.com and click on subscribe so we
can keep you posted of information that may be of
importance. Thank you. Now, back to the chat with
our guest. So, there's copy trading platforms,
and I'm not sure if you're referring to those,
where it's much more retail focused. Um, you
could piggyback on a retail trader and and follow
their trades. We when we started fund seedar we
always felt that you know we're trying to find a
handful of top traders and then help them become
institutional so that they can compete against
some of the bigger hedge funds out there. So, we
we're more focused on the institutional investors
versus retail investors that could kind of copy
or or piggyback on a trader that's that's making
money and then providing them with with the
infrastructure around it. Uh tell us a little
bit about RQSI. Um what is that? Yeah. So, as
I mentioned, you know, when Jack and I founded
Fund Cedar, we had this idea um of finding
talent, but we found out that it was much more
difficult to transition from even just finding
the talent to creating a scalable business. So,
RQSI acquired FundSeeder and FundSeeder is part
of RQSI. The founder Neil Ramsey um was an early
seeder in in in in many managers. So he seeded I
think just over 20 managers that went on to manage
over $20 billion in PKUM. Some of your listeners
might know some Fort QIM uh was early with Crael
and uh and then he transitioned and built a a stat
model that went up to about over $2 billion and or
I've known him for five or six years and he's been
working on uh a systematic global macro program
and the returns just stopped working and you know
when when he when we reconnected he said look I'm
going to back to my roots. I I really believe that
there are talented traders out there and that we
can help by giving first capital, providing seed
capital to them and not only that but mentorship
and whatever infrastructure that they might need
so that they have an opportunity to grow and
scale. So best was a big piece of the puzzle uh in
terms of the fund seater journey because now you
have capital that's being allocated and you have a
person like Neil Ramsey and RQSI that has actually
a history of seeding some managers that have gone
on to manage billions of dollars. Uh so your main
focus for investors are institutional investors.
Correct. Correct. Okay. And then uh kind of so
then what's the main since they have access to
lots of you know ETFs and fund managers mutual
funds and so forth um what's the selling point for
them to uh invest with this group of kind of new
trader relatively new traders that are not nearly
as well known as the people on Wall Street. If you
think about some of the largest funds out there,
they're multi-pod shops, right? The Millenniums
of the world, the the the 72s, the Citadels, and
these, you know, these firms are only allocating
to the big established PMs or you're hearing
about the talent wars and one, you know, one
one manager moves from one firm to another. And so
what we're trying to do is we're trying to create,
you know, this baseball farm system, if you will,
of the smaller managers and giving them that first
capital and providing them with uh the ability to
to to scale and grow at a pace that makes sense.
So from an investor perspective, if you're an
investor and you and you believe in emerging
managers, you believe in u traders that have edge
and they're not they don't have to be working for
some of the largest firms, that's something
that you know makes makes this compelling.
Uh so for all the traders out there um can
you illustrate just a few benefits of signing
up for your platform um that they can get uh and
perhaps maybe help improve their trading or their
uh the way they do things um how can an
average trader benefit? Sure there so
there's two pieces. The first is if you're just a
trader and you're looking to have some analytics
um they're free that um you know you currently
don't have u at your brokerage firm you sign up
to fund cedar not only you're going to get these
analytics that you could see how your performance
uh you know compares and some of these metrics we
talked about earlier but you could actually see
how you can compare against other people in your
peer group. So extremely valuable. Most of the
most traders that I know are trading in a silo.
They, you know, they have no idea how they stack
up against their peers. Maybe monthly they see how
the hedge fund index perform. But by and large,
um, it's, you know, they have they don't
have that comparison and funded provides
that. The second piece, and this is for the top
1%, and and I'm hopeful that there's some of your
um listeners uh or even some that have been on
this show, that if they if they want to make
that next step to to manage money, um that they
apply to funded rise, which is the accelerator,
um and this is this is a much more curated
exclusive uh um program. Um and and and the
and the traders that we do accept, we will work
with them to to help them scale and become uh
institutional money managers. Fantastic. Is there
a uh cost to sign up? No cost. Okay, great. So to
wrap up, how can our listeners uh reach both of
you, Jack? Yeah. Um I do have on uh on X um I I
sometimes some grativity on that. So uh just my
name Jack Schwager. Um I have my website but I I
really don't update it anymore. There's some old
stuff on there uh which is jackshagger.com and
uh I guess I could be contacted through FundSeeder
as well. Fantastic Emanuel. Yeah, just go to
funseeder.com and um again this the accelerator
we're opening it up for another few weeks or so.
So if you want to apply or if you know someone
um we would appreciate any any referrals or
recommendations of the next market wizards if you
will that also have aspirations of of of being the
next hedge fund manager. Fantastic. Thank you very
much for uh coming on Chat with Traders. Thank you
Ian. Thanks. All right. I hope you enjoyed Ian's
conversation with Jack and Emanuel, and I also had
the great pleasure of chatting with both of them
for a few minutes after the interview. While I
think that the reality is that very few traders
ever make the leap to managing outside capital,
think about this. Every fund manager who did
started out like many of us at some point,
trading their own account and steadily building
their track record. I told them how appreciative
I am on behalf of traders everywhere in the
world for their contributions bringing to us this
amazing opportunity and possibility and giving us
something to aim for. The great part too is that
even if you don't make it into the accelerator,
you can still sign up at fundseeder.com
for free to get analytics on your trading and
see how you can stack up against other traders
around the world. And that alone can be a
powerful tool to help you improve in your
trading journey. And if you have been honing
your craft and building a strong track record,
or maybe you're closer than you think.
Honestly, I know that some of you listening
are ready right now for this next step.
And I say go for it. We're rooting for you.
You've reached the end of this episode
of Chat with Traders, but rest assured,
there are more episodes loaded with real
market insight and zero hype on the way soon.
So, to stay updated with each great new release,
subscribe to the podcast in iTunes, and we'd love
it if you'd leave a rating and review. We'll
catch you next time on Chat with Traders.
[Music]